College of Humanities and Social Sciences Records 1913-1999 1960-1989
Carnegie Mellon University
1913-1999
29 Boxes (Box 1-29); 29 cubic feet
Carnegie Mellon University Archives
College of Humanities and Social Science
Carnegie-Mellon University.; Carnegie Institute of Technology.; Carnegie Institute of Technology. Dept. of English; Carnegie-Mellon University. Dept. of Humanities and Social Science; Carnegie Mellon University. Dept. of History and Social Sciences; Carnegie-Mellon University. Dept. of Modern Languages; Carnegie-Mellon University. Dept. of Philosophy; Carnegie-Mellon University. Dept. of Psychology; Carnegie-Mellon University. Communications Design Center
Records History
During the first years of the Carnegie Institute of Technology (CIT), each of the colleges that comprised CIT employed their own teachers of academic humanities subjects -- Economics, English, History, Mathematics, Modern Languages, and Psychology. In 1917, a planned restructuring brought teachers of like subjects together into a Central Faculty. World War I prevented implementation of the restructuring until 1919, at which time the Central Faculty was renamed the Division of Academic Studies. Shortly thereafter, the administration approved a name change to the Division of General Studies.
Most viewed the Division as a "service" unit, providing academic humanities courses for male students pursuing degrees in the "technical" Divisions of Science and Engineering Arts, Industries, or Applied Psychology. The final Division, Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, provided liberal arts courses for women.
In 1941, the Division of General Studies was reorganized into the Division of Humanistic and Social Studies. Reorganization provided an opportunity for the new Division to overcome the "service" niche in which General Studies had existed. By 1950, the new Division had become a vital part of Carnegie Tech. Students from other Divisions were increasingly taking more humanities courses. This was especially true of the female students at Margaret Morrison. In the 1950s, there was a concerted effort to integrate Margaret Morrison and Engineering and Science students into H and SS courses. In 1962, the administration approved another name change. The Division of Humanistic and Social Studies became the Division of Humanities and Social Sciences.
In 1967, discussion of a "new college for Carnegie Tech" began. Efforts were made to bring the humanities departments together into a cohesive unit and the first class of the "New College" entered in September 1969. However, problems plagued the program from the start and it did not long survive.
During the mid-1970s, the administration took steps to reorganize the collection of departments they had recently acknowledged as the College of Humanities and Social Sciences. The various departments, in truth, had become disjointed, haphazard, and were lacking a common goal. The reorganization of the mid-1970s also included women who would have attended Margaret Morrison, for the college had graduated its last class in the spring of 1969.
The late 1970s and early 1980s saw the development of a core curriculum and the adoption of the phrase "liberal professional education" as an integral part of the mission of the College. The core curriculum and defined mission aided departments in establishing a base on which the College could grow. Statistics formally joined the College in 1981. Philosophy separated from History, becoming its own department, in 1985. The Education Center, which had operated within the college for approximately 15 years, was given a university-wide mission and renamed the University Teaching Center. The academic departments within the College underwent reviews by outside visiting committees during the late 1980s and early 1990s. These efforts were made as an effort to upgrade the image of the College.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains records of the College of Humanities and Social Sciences which are arranged in three series; Series 1: College of Humanities and Social Science, which contains records created by the College as a whole; Series 2: Departments, which contains records produced by the Economics, English, History, Philosophy, Modern Languages, Political Science, Psychology, Social Science, and Statistics departments, as well as some records from the Margaret Morrison Carnegie College; and Series 3: Publications, which houses publications produced by the departments of English and History. The collection spans the period from 1913 through 1999. Except for annual reports, the records are rather lacking from the early years through the 1940s. There are increasingly more records from the 1950s. The bulk of the records span the 1960s through the 1980s. There are a limited number of records from the 1990s.
Provenance
This collection was transferred from the Dean's office of the College of Humanities and Social Sciences to the University Archives in stages. The material included in this inventory had reached the Archives by January 2000.
Restrictions
Information pertaining to personnel procedures, information covered by FERPA, and any salary information will be restricted accordingly.
Separations
None.
Collection List
- College of Humanities and Social Science, This series is arranged in the following Subseries: History of the College of HSS Annual Reports Councils Plans Budget/Financial Matters Student Information Administrative Information Faculty Centers Surveys/Studies Correspondence Publications Newsclippings Curriculum Graduate Program Special Programs
  - History of the College of HSS
    - Humanities Institute, 1969
    - History of HSS--"Discourses upon the History of HSS", 1974
    - History of HSS--College Creation, 1967-1969
    - History of HSS--"Building from Strength", date unknown
    - History of HSS--College Creation, date unknown
    - History of HSS--Division Reorganization, 1947
    - History of HSS--Goals Committee, 1966
    - History of HSS--Goals Committee, 1967
    - History of HSS--Goals Committee, 1968
    - History of HSS--Goals Committee, 1970
    - History of HSS--Goals Committee, 1971
    - History of HSS--Goals Committee, 1971[2]
    - History of HSS--Goals Committee, 1972
    - History of HSS--Goals Committee, date unknown
    - History of HSS--College Creation--Position Papers--R. Cyert, E. Steinberg, 1967
    - History of HSS--Position Paper--"The Present and Future of HSS", 1976
    - History of HSS--Pamphlets, 1969
    - History of HSS--Newsclippings, 1970
    - Middle States Association Accreditation Report, 1976
    - CMU Case Statement, 1976
    - Middle States Association Accreditation Report, 1976
    - Middle States Accreditation Committee, date unknown
    - Middle States Evaluation Team Report, 1988
  - Annual Reports
    - Annual Report--Department of General Studies, 1913-1914
    - Annual Report--Division of Academic Studies, 1918-1919
    - Annual Report--Division of Academic Studies, 1919-1920
    - Annual Report--Division of Academic Studies, 1920-1921
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1922-1923
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1923-1924
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1924-1925
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1925-1926
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1926-1927
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1927-1928
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1928-1929
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1929-1930
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1930-1931
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1931-1932
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1932-1933
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1933-1934
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1934-1935
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1935-1936
    - Annual Report--Department of Management Engineering, 1935-1936
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1936-1937
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1937-1938
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1938-1939
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1939-1940
    - Annual Report--Division of General Studies, 1940-1941
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1941-1942
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1942-1943
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1942-1943[2]
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1943-1944
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1943-1944[2]
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1944-1945
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1944-1945[2]
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1945-1946
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1945-1946[2]
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1946-1947
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1946-1947[2]
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1947-1948
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1947-1948[2]
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1948-1949
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1948-1949[2]
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1949-1950
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1951-1952
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1952-1953
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1952-1953[2]
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1953-1954
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1953-1954[2]
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1954-1955
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1954-1955[2]
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1955-1956
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1955-1956[2]
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1956-1957
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1956-1957[2]
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1957-1958
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1958-1959
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1959-1960
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1960-1961
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1960-1961[2]
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1961-1962
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1961-1962[2]
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1962-1963
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1963-1964
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1964-1965
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1964-1965[2]
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies/Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, 1965-1966
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies/Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, 1965-1966[2]
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanistic and Social Studies, 1965-1966
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanities and Social Sciences/Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, 1966-1967
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanities and Social Sciences/Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, 1966-1967[2]
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanities and Social Sciences/Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, 1967-1968
    - Annual Report--Division of Humanities and Social Sciences/Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, 1967-1968[2]
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1967-1968
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1968-1969
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences/Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, 1968-1969
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences/Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, 1968-1969[2]
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences/Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, 1968-1969[3]
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences/Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, 1969-1970
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences/Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, 1969-1970[2]
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1970-1971
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1970-1971[2]
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences/Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, 1971-1972
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences/Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, 1971-1972[2]
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences/Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, 1972-1973
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences/Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, 1972-1973[2]
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences/Margaret Morrison Carnegie College, 1972-1973[3]
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1973-1974
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1973-1974[2]
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1974-1975
    - College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1974-1975[2]
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1975-1976
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1975-1976[2]
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1975-1976[3]
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1976-1977
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1976-1977[2]
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1977-1978
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1978-1979
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1979-1980
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1980-1981
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1980-1981[2]
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1981-1982
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1981-1982[2]
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1981-1982[3]
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1982-1983
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1982-1983[2]
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1984-1985
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1986-1987
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1986-1987[2]
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1987-1988
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1988-1989
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1988-1989[2]
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1989-1990
    - Annual Report--College of Humanities and Social Sciences, 1989-1990
  - Councils
    - Divisional Council Minutes, 1949-1950
    - Divisional Council Minutes, 1950-1951,1951-1952
    - Divisional Council Minutes, 1952-1953
    - Divisional Council--Subcommittee on Scholarship--Minutes, 1949-1953
    - Divisional Council--Minutes, 1953-1954
    - Divisional Council--Minutes, 1954-1955
    - Divisional Council--Minutes, 1955-1956
    - Divisional Council--Minutes, 1956-1957
    - Divisional Council--Minutes, 1957-1958
    - Divisional Council--Minutes, 1958-1959
    - Divisional Council--Minutes, 1959-1960
    - Divisional Council--Minutes, 1960-1961
    - Divisional Council--Minutes, 1961-1962
    - Divisional Council--Minutes, 1962-1963
    - Divisional Council--Minutes, 1963-1964
    - Divisional Council--Minutes, 1965-1967
    - Dean’s Council, 1980
    - Dean’s Council, 1981
    - Dean’s Council, 1982
    - Dean’s Council, 1983
    - Dean’s Council, 1984
    - Dean’s Council, 1984[2]
    - Dean’s Council, 1985
    - Dean’s Council, 1987
    - College Council, 1966-1968
    - College Council, 1969
    - College Council, 1969[2]
    - College Council, 1970
    - College Council, 1970[2]
    - College Council, 1970[3]
    - College Council, 1970[4]
    - College Council, 1970[5]
    - College Council, 1971
    - College Council, 1971[2]
    - College Council, 1972
    - College Council, 1972[2]
    - College Council, 1973
    - College Council, 1973[2]
    - College Council, 1974
    - College Council, 1977
    - College Council, 1978
    - College Council, 1979
    - College Council, 1980
    - College Council, 1981
    - College Council, 1982
    - College Council, 1983
    - College Council, 1984
    - College Council, 1984[2]
    - College Council, 1985
    - College Council, 1986
    - Educational Affairs Council, 1977
    - Educational Affairs Council, 1978
    - Educational Affairs Council, 1979
    - Educational Affairs Council, 1980
    - Educational Affairs Council, 1981
    - Educational Affairs Council, 1982
    - Educational Affairs Council, 1983
  - Plans
    - Five Year Plan, 1980-1985
    - Five Year Plan, 1981-1986
    - Five Year Plan, 1981-1986[2]
    - Five Year Plan, 1964-1969
    - Five Year Plan, 1985-1990
    - Departmental Plans, 1966, 1968
  - Budget/Financial Matters
    - Professional Development Fund, 1959-1963
    - Budget--Social Science, 1980-1981
    - Budget, 1981-1983
    - Budget--Correspondence, 1981-1983
    - Budget--Core Curriculum, 1985-1987
    - Business Manager’s Council, 1988-1989
    - Tuition Exchange Plan, 1955
    - Lilly Endowment Proposal, 1977
    - Survey Summary--Department Expenditures, 1978-1983
    - Fellowships, 1984
    - Carnegie-Mellon University F.I.P.S.E. Proposal, 1988
    - Brochure--Capital Campaign, date unknown
    - Crewe, Albert V., et. al.--"Private Universities and Private Giving", 1972
    - Enos, Richard Leo--"A Preliminary Report of the Project Funded by the President’s Fund for Scholarship in the Humanities", 1982
    - Westinghouse/CMU Contract in Robotics, 1981, 1982
    - President’s Fund and Ford Grants, 1981
    - President’s Fund and Ford Grant’s, 1981[2]
    - President’s Fund--Application Information, 1981
    - President’s Fund--Achenbaum, W. Andrew, 1981
    - President’s Fund--Barrett, Lynne, 1981
    - President’s Fund--Carrier, David, 1981
    - President’s Fund--Costanzo, Gerald, 1981
    - President’s Fund--Jones, Ilsedore, 1981-1982
    - President’s Fund--Enos, Richard Leo, 1981
    - President’s Fund--Flower, Linda, 1981
    - President’s Fund--Hart, John A., 1981
    - President’s Fund--Hayes, Ann, 1981
    - President’s Fund--Kaiser, David, 1981-1982
    - President’s Fund--Kaufer, David S., 1981
    - President’s Fund--Knapp, Peggy, 1981
    - President’s Fund--Levy, Eugene and David Demarest, 1981, 1982
    - President’s Fund--Miller, David, 1981
    - President’s Fund--Silenieks, Juris, 1981
    - President’s Fund--Weber, Michael, 1981-1983
    - President’s Fund--Fowler, David, 1982
    - President’s Fund--Hallstein, Christian, 1982
    - President’s Fund--Sutton, Donald, 1982
    - President’s Fund--Barnes, Andrew, 1983
    - President’s Fund--Constant II, Edward, 1983
    - President’s Fund--Covey, Preston, 1983
    - President’s Fund--Lynch, Katherine, 1983
    - President’s Fund--Rose, Anne C., 1983
    - Truman Scholarship Program, 1980
    - Van Horn, Richard, et. al.--"Liberal Education for Professionals", date unknown
    - Wands, John--"Report on President’s Fund for Research in the Humanities", 1981
  - Student Records
    - Admission--Statistics, 1979-1982
    - Admission--Graduate Statistics, 1977-1979
    - Enrollment--General, 1961-1962, 1965-1966
    - Enrollment--Gains and Losses, 1978-1983
    - Enrollment--Class Size Study, 1975-1976
    - Enrollment--General Statistics, 1969, 1974-1979, 1980
    - Enrollment--Undergraduate Statistics, 1983
    - Enrollment--Undergraduate, 1978-1981
    - Enrollment--Undergraduate, 1982-1983
    - Enrollment--Undergraduate, 1983
    - Enrollment--Graduate, 1983
    - Enrollment--Economics, 1974
    - Enrollment--English, 1975-1976, 1977-1978
    - Enrollment--History/Philosophy, 1971-1981, 1982
    - Freshman Orientation, 1955
    - Senior Credit Shortages, 1963, 1965
    - "Free Seminar", 1969
    - Student-Defined Majors, 1973-1981
    - Degrees Granted, 1976-1978
    - Grade Statistics, Fall 1977
    - Performances in Core Courses, Fall 1978
    - Academic Progress, 1979-1982
    - Undergraduate Catalog, 1979-1981
    - Graduate Catalog, 1987-1988
    - Dean’s List, Fall 1980
    - Dean’s List, Spring 1981
    - Dean’s List, Fall 1981
    - Graduates, 1983
    - Graduates, 1984
    - Freshman Guidebook, 1983-1984
    - Freshman Guidebook, 1984-1985
    - Freshman Guidebook, 1991
    - Add/Drop Procedures, date unknown
    - Underclass Letter, date unknown
    - Report--Grades and Class Size, Fall 1979
    - Report--Grades and Class Size, Spring 1980
    - Report--Grades and Class Size, Fall 1980
    - Report--Grades and Class Size, Spring 1981
  - Administrative Information
    - Administration--Review Committee, 1963
    - Administration--Presidential Evaluation Report, 1982
    - Administration--President Cyert’s Inauguration, 1973
    - Administration--President Cyert Evaluation, 1987
    - Administration--Presidential Search--1989-1990
    - Administration--Dean’s Information, 1973-1974
    - Administration--Dean Search, 1983-1987, 1991
    - Administration--Dean’s Report, 1989-1990
    - Administration--Provost Search, 1990
    - Administration--Crecine, John--1987
    - Administration--"Fair Labor Standards Act", 1969
    - Administration--Board of Trustees Agenda, 1983
    - Administration--"Administrative Systems as Applied", 1984
    - Administration--Addition to Baker Hall, 1999
    - Administration--General Correspondence, 1965-1967
    - Administration--General Correspondence, 1982-1986
    - Administration--"Pittsburgh Council on Higher Education", 1984
  - Faculty
    - Faculty--Constitution, 1948, 1949, 1959
    - Faculty--Meeting Minutes, 1943-1945
    - Faculty--Meeting Minutes, 1946-1949
    - Faculty--Meeting Minutes, 1949-1951
    - Faculty--Meeting Minutes, 1951-1956
    - Faculty--Meeting Minutes, 1956-1958
    - Faculty--Meeting Minutes, 1958-1961
    - Faculty--Meeting Minutes, 1961-1963
    - Faculty--Meeting Minutes, 1963-1967
    - Faculty--Meeting Minutes, 1970
    - Faculty Senate Meetings, 1975-1981
    - Faculty Senate Meetings, 1982-1984
    - Faculty Appointments, 1936-1940
    - Faculty Appointments, 1941-1944
    - Faculty Appointments, 1945-1949
    - Faculty Appointments, 1950-1956
    - Faculty Appointments, 1957-1961
    - Faculty Appointments, 1964-1965
    - Faculty Appointments, 1989, 1994
    - Faculty Roster, 1926-1948
    - Faculty Roster, 1948-1955
    - Faculty Roster, 1955-1962
    - Faculty--Teaching Loads, 1974-1983
    - Faculty--Teaching Loads, 1980
    - Faculty--Promotion Criteria, 1950
    - Faculty--Promotion and Tenure Review Policy, 1965
    - Faculty--Numbers by Department, 1977-1978, 1978-1979
    - Faculty--Faculty Student Ratio, Fall 1978
    - Faculty--Committee on Grading, 1970
    - Faculty--Tenure Guidelines, 1973-1978
    - Faculty--Student Evaluation Form [blank], circa 1975
    - Faculty--Achievement Certificate [blank], date unknown
    - Faculty--Reception Invitations, 1967, 1977, 1993
    - Faculty--Hayes, John R.--"Research, Teaching, and Faculty Fate", 1971
    - Faculty--Kirk, Jerome--"On Understanding Students", 1966
    - Faculty--Sochatoff, A. Fred--"Report on the School--College Orientation Program in Pittsburgh; (SCOPP)", date unknown
    - Faculty--General Correspondence, 1955
    - Faculty--General Correspondence, 1956
    - Faculty--General Correspondence, 1987-1988
    - Faculty--Memoranda, 1942
    - Faculty--Memoranda, 1950-1951
    - Faculty--Memoranda, 1956-1958
    - Faculty--Memoranda, 1963-1967